If this video tells me I'm gonna have to
stop drinking coffee, I'm going to lose
my
mind. Hey pal, I know what's going
through every fiber of your being, but
relax. We're going to get through this
together. Put down the knife. In an
interview, Dr. Paul Paul Pal I wrote
pal. Dr. Paul Saladino, a boardcertified
physician with a board certification as
a physician nutrition specialist, gave
multiple reasons for why no one on Earth
should drink coffee for any reason. And
if you're on the space station, I
respect the dedication, but you aren't
getting a pass either. Cries an
astronaut. Let's listen in and we'll pop
open some studies to find out what's
what. So, you don't drink coffee? I
don't drink coffee at all. Okay, because
you've never mentioned it. I've listened
to a few of your videos. You've never
mentioned coffee. Why don't you drink
coffee? Um, okay. So, this is a whole
thing and your audience is going to hate
me. I don't hate you, Paul, but I really
can't speak for them. Just don't take
away their coffee. Go for it. Okay.
They're going to hate both of us at the
end of Well, they're they're especially
going to hate me because we're hopefully
we're also going to talk about
chocolate. You're making this very
difficult, Paul. Please stop. Yeah.
Yeah. But um so a couple things about
coffee. So what is coffee? Coffee is a
seed from a plant. And when I think
about plants and the parts of plants
that plants don't want you to eat, seeds
are probably some of the most highly
defended parts of plants. So we're
talking nuts, which are seeds, grains,
we talked about oats and quinoa, but
also wheat, etc. People know those
grains. Um beans, like a coffee quote
bean, which are legumes, or black beans
or lentils. And then nuts, right? We
talk nuts, grains, seeds, and legumes,
right? Those are all seeds because if
you plant them in the ground, they grow
into a plant. We just call them
different things, but they're all seeds.
That's a plant baby. Meaning that if
that gets eaten by an animal and the
animal is just says, "Oh, that tasted
great. No problem." And it just gives
the animal nutrients. Those plants are
never going to evolve because those
animals are just going to eat the heck
out of those seeds. So the the the
plants will put defense chemicals in the
seeds. And seeds are very highly
defended. We talked about sapinins, we
talked about phytic acid, we've talked a
little bit about oxalates, but in the
case of coffee, you have defense
chemicals in the seeds of that plant. um
like anything else. Okay, coffee is a
seed and it contains defense chemicals
in it that make it unhealthy to consume
because the plants are trying to stop
animals, us from consuming them. Makes
some sense. And I don't have the
background to assess the validity of
what plants want or don't want. I'd
guess someone with a botney degree or
something to that effect might be able
to speak to it. I'm clueless. However, I
should point out that coffee also
contains many beneficial molecules like
polyphenols and flavonols. These
molecules are intimately tied to
improvements in our cells functionality
through the elimination of damaging
molecules like free radicals by acting
as antioxidants to increase the
production of nitric oxide which reduces
blood pressure as well as reducing
inflammation. One critically important
one is chlorogenic acid which has been
shown many times over according to that
scientific review to stimulate a potent
antioxidant pathway in our cells called
the NRF2 pathway. This protein nrf2 when
activated will move into the nucleus of
your cells and bind antioxidant genes
like HO1 and NQ1 and lead to their
reading by the gene reading machinery in
your cells thereby making more of these
potent proteins that eliminate damaging
molecules in our cells as well as
breaking down highly reactive hem
molecules that would otherwise wreak
havoc on our cellular structure and
integrity. I'm massively glossing over
the number of ways these flavonols and
polyphenols have been directly shown to
improve cellular function, but that's
just a taste. Now, to be fair, we could
do the exact same thing with some of the
molecules that Dr. Saladino mentions
because there are harmful molecules in
coffee, too. Fortunately, we can still
get clear answers, which we'll get to.
By the way, I'll reiterate that I don't
have any background in how plants want
to poison us and stop us from consuming
them, but I have this vague memory
hearing that some plants are consumed by
animals, which leads to their greater
propagation since the animal will end up
releasing some seeds out of their
backend, populating that plant with
fertilizer in a new location. Am I
crazy? Again, not my area of expertise,
but if you do have some background in
this, I'd be keen to know if there's
some merit to that idea. We'll consider
it the anti- Saladonian plant hypothesis
described by the ever clueless Professor
Verhovven. Now, I just need a a like a
pipe and make a have like massive
sideburns or a massive mustache as I
scoff at the alternative ideas like this
guy. I have no idea who this is. Anyway,
moving on. Damn it. Caffeine is actually
a defense chemical that the plant puts
there. Now, interestingly, in the doses
we have with caffeine, um it it it
reinforces eating the beans because of
the way that caffeine affects dopamine
in human brain. And who knows why this
is, but it it's a problematic thing for
humans. I think mostly from the
perspective of sleep. So, no one wants
to hear this, but the quarter life of
caffeine is 12 hours, 10 to 12 hours.
Meaning that if you drink a cup of
coffee at let's say 8:00 a.m. or 9:00
a.m. in the morning, a lot of people are
waiting now like 90 minutes after they
wake up to drink their coffee. So
depending when you wake up, when you
drink your first cup of coffee, an
average cup of coffee has 150 milligrams
to 200 milligrams of caffeine in it. So
that 200 milligrams of caffeine, if you
drink one single cup of coffee, a
quarter of that is still in your body
affecting the physiology of your brain
to initiate sleep, to help you through
the sleep stages 12 hours after you
drink the coffee. So if you drink coffee
at 8 or 9 and you go to sleep at 9 or
10, you still have about a quarter of
the coffee, the quarter of the caffeine,
excuse me. So 50 milligrams of caffeine
in your body at that point. Now, how is
that affecting your sleep stages? This
is really the elephant in the room that
no one wants to talk about. So doing
that every day. Now that's that's pretty
benign. One cup of coffee, quote benign,
at 9:00 a.m. I don't do it. And I'm
saying benign relative to what I'm going
to describe next, which is probably a
more typical pattern for people, which
is cup of coffee at 8, cup of coffee at
10:00, and maybe coffee at 1 or two.
Now, at that point, the halflife of
caffeine means you got half of the
caffeine at 6 hours. So, if you drink
coffee at 1 or 2 and you go to sleep at
10 p.m., you got a lot of caffeine in
your body and you've got all of the
cumulative caffeine in your body. So,
say you have three cups of coffee
throughout the day. That's 600 milligs
of caffeine. And you have them at three
different parts throughout the day. You
could potentially have 200 milligs of
caffeine still in your body when you go
to sleep or 150, which is the equivalent
of 3/4 of a cup of coffee right before
you go to sleep. Okay, here Dr. Saladino
does bring up a great point. It's true
that caffeine can affect sleep, and it's
not just one's ability to fall asleep,
but he astutely points out sleep
architecture. Your sleep isn't just you
passed out on the couch with Cheetos
spilled all over your shirt watching
this video. It's a back and forth
shifting of gears between the different
stages of deep sleep as well as rapid
eye movement sleep or REM sleep. The
brain and body must go through these
stages with the appropriate amounts of
time in each because each stage performs
different functions for our biology.
It's a fascinating field of science that
I hope to produce more investigations on
in the future. But for now, just know
that the caffeine molecule due to its
similarity to a sleepromoting molecule
adenosine will bind to the same
receptors as adenosine without
activating them and out compete
adenosine thereby blocking sleep. And
even if sleep occurs, it might be a
different architecture or quality. This
is just one way. There are other
mechanisms. So to Dr. To Saladino's
point, if we look at this systematic
review, the researchers compared people
told to consume caffeine against people
told not to consume caffeine. Those that
survive, that is, that was a joke. And
we can see across multiple metrics of
sleep architecture, the three different
nonREM stages and the one REM stage,
there are changes. Sleep efficiency is
reduced. That's indicated because it
moves to the left of that zero line
there when people consume caffeine.
There's also a bit more of stage one
sleep and possibly reduce sleep, stage
three sleep. So, Dr. Sadino is spoton
and long-term poor sleep can manifest in
a host of diseases. The most robust
evidence is behind the total sleep, but
there's some murmurings in relation to
sleep architecture, too. But I would be
cautious about overinterpreting those
data. Anyway, one easy solution then is
to simply drink decaf, right? I mean,
problem solved, except you still have to
deal with the seed problem. We'll
address that shortly. First, let's hear
if decaf coffee, which is nonsense,
might provide a solution. How do you
feel about decaf? So, decaf usually has
much much less caffeine. So, you're
doing a much better thing for your body,
but there are still other problems with
coffee and caffeine because it's still
seeds at the end. It's still a seed.
There are mold toxins, right, in a lot
of coffees, unless it's a wet product.
That's what's scaring me right now. I
feel like everything's moldy. A lot of
grains are moldy because you also get
mold on oats. So, that's back to the
oats. We didn't even talk about that
with oatmeal. Yet, another reason not to
eat oatmeal. Even it's organic oatmeal.
Okay. Mold in our coffee, mold in our
oats, it's doing us all harm. Let me
backtrack here a bit because there's
some more discussion to be had on
caffeine and sleep. I'm going to cover
that in the extended version of this
video that you're watching. So, if
you're interested in more scientific
breakdowns, written research reviews,
shortened summaries, templates, guides,
live sessions with me, and more,
consider joining the Physionic Insiders.
You get all of that stuff in one place.
Not to mention the awesome community
that's over there. Hope to talk with you
over some moldy coffee over there. And
the link is in the description if you
care to join. Back to moldy coffee
murdering us slowly. So decaf coffee
eliminates or drastically lessens the
sleep issue, but it's still a seed and
now a moldy seed at that. Okay, this
happens a lot on social media, but we
get so focused on the mechanisms and
side quests that we miss the forest for
the trees. The real question is what
happens when people consume coffee? Do
they die more? Do they experience
disease more often? The answer is
no. If we look at long-term over decades
of coffee consumption and we compare
people who don't drink coffee to people
who do drink coffee, there's a reduced
risk of cardiovascular mortality. And we
can see that because the line goes down
from the neutral one on the vertical
axis with the coffee consumption on the
horizontal axis. We see a similar result
looking at death from all causes. Again,
reduce risk. This is also after
adjusting for many different explanatory
factors. There are several randomized
control trials on coffee as well. Some
show seemingly negative effects like
increases in blood pressure, but there
are also studies indicating overall
benefits of cardioabolic health. The
research all considered points in the
direction of mixed results on short-term
studies and generally improvements in
multiple disease risks from long-term
studies. So overall, regardless of the
molds and the different harmful
molecules, the net effect indicates a
positive outcome from coffee consumption
within reason. Of course, it's still
true that drinking coffee later in the
day can drastically interfere with your
sleep quality. So all in all, I would
disagree with Dr. Saladino that coffee
is something to be avoided on average.
It's generally a positive for health
unless abused, much like most things. So
like I said, relax. You didn't need to
threaten me at the beginning. You can
keep drinking your coffee. In fact, I
cover if coffee can compare against tea
right here. One is a clear winner. I'll
catch you over there.